Guide to the Clifford Odets papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Clifford Odets Papers,
1937-1964
[Bulk Dates: 1945-1963]
Odets, Clifford, 1906-1963
6 linear ft. (6 record containers)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library New York, NY. 10027
MS#1636
9746888
Clifford Odets was an American playwright. He was born in 1906 to Russian and Romanian immigrants. Odets dropped out of high school, striking out on his own to pursue a career in acting. He was a founding member of the Group Theatre in New York that utilized a new technique in acting based on the ideas of Constantin Stanislavski. The Group Theatre was further developed by director Lee Strasberg. Odets was married twice, both to actresses: Luise Rainer and Bette Grayson. The collection consists of his original plays and screenplays, including drafts. These were at one time loaned to Margaret Brenman-Gibson for work on her biography of Odets, which was published in 1981. There is a small section of personal papers that includes clippings, correspondence, ephemera, notes, and his secretary's appointment book.
Biographical Note
Clifford Odets was an important American playwright. He was born in 1906 in Philadelphia to Russian and Romanian immigrants. Odets struck out on his own, dropping out of high school, to pursue a career in acting. He was a founding member of the Group Theatre in New York that utilized a new technique in acting based on the ideas of Constantin Stanislavski. The Group Theatre was further developed by director Lee Strasberg. Odets was married twice, both to actresses: Luise Rainer and Bette Grayson. With Grayson, he had two children, Nora and Walt. Odets wrote plays and screenplays, perhaps, best known for his Waiting for Lefty, Awake and Sing, and Golden Boy. In 1952, Odets was called before the House Un-American Activities Committee. He had belonged to the CPUSA for less than a year between 1934-1935. In his final years, Odets worked with NBC's The Richard Boone Show. Odets died of colon cancer at the age of 57.
Scope and Content
The collection primarily consists of original and copied plays and screenplays written or adapted by Clifford Odets. The earliest of these is his Waiting for Lefty from 1938. For some of the writings there are multiple copies as well as first, second, and third drafts. There are treatments by Walter Newman and research notebooks for The Way West. The Clifford Odets Papers also contains a small series of personal papers. These items are in the main from 1960-1963 and consist of clippings, ephemera, playbills, programs, and serials. There are a few pieces of correspondence including an anniversary announcement from Lee and Paula Strasberg, as well as from Milton Lipper to the Strasberg's following Odets' death in 1963.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in two series:
Series I: Plays and Screenplays, 1938-1963
Series II: Personal Papers, 1937-1964
Subjects
Odets, Clifford, 1906-1963; Dramatists, American; Plays; Screenplays; Scripts (documents)
Access Restrictions
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least 2 business days in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
William Gibson Gift July 2011 2011.2012.M135
The Clifford Odets Papers were the gift of William Gibson to the Rare Book and Manuscript Library at Columbia University in July of 2011. The materials originally came in as part of the Margaret Brenman-Gibson Papers MS#1635, but were separated because of provenance.
Selected Related Material -- at Columbia
Margaret Brenman-Gibson Papers, Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Columbia University
Selected Related Material -- at Outside Repositories
Clifford Odets Papers, The Billy Rose Theatre Division, New York Public Library for the Performing Arts
Clifford Odets Papers, Lilly Library, Indiana University
Finding aid online and in repository folder level control
- Series I: Plays and Screenplays, 1938-1963
  Series I consists of original and copied plays and screenplays written or adapted by Clifford Odets. The works range in date from Waiting for Lefty from 1938 to the scripts he did for The Richard Boone Show in 1963. Present in this series are first, second, and third drafts as well as final versions of plays and screenplays.
  - The Big Knife
    - 1948, undated, (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - Third Draft, (copy) circa 1948-1949, (3 folders) (Box 1)
    - Partial (copy), undated (Box 1)
    - Screenplay by James Poe (from the play by Clifford Odets), undated, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - The Children's Story (working title), 1945 May (Box 1)
  - Country Girl
    - Second Draft, (copy) 1949, (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - Third Draft (copy), 1949 October 25 (Box 1)
    - Third Draft (copy), undated, (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - Fourth Draft (copy), 1950 August (Box 1)
    - Fourth Draft (copy), undated, (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - Final, As Being Played (copy), 1949, (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - Uncut Version, 1949 October 17, (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - Uncut Version (copy), 1949 October 17, (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Early Notes and Scenes (copy), 1949, (3 folders) (Box 2)
    - Notes (copy), undated (Box 2)
    - Production Notes (copy), 1950, (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Deadline at Dawn--Final Script, 1945 April 16, (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - The Greatest Gift
    - 1945 January 25, (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - undated, (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Incomplete, 1945 February26 (Box 2)
  - Joseph and His Brethren
    - First Estimating Draft, 1954 May 10, (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Second Estimating Draft, 1954 December 30, (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - The Murder Story (working title)--First Draft, undated, (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Night Music, 1940, (3 folders) (Box 2)
  - Night Music, 1940 (Box 3)
  - None but the Lonely Heart (adapted from Richard Llewellyn's novel)--Second Draft Continuity (revised), 1943 December 18, (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - North Star (The Richard Boone Show)
    - 1963 April 10 (Box 3)
    - First Revision, 1963 April 26 (Box 3)
  - The Olympian--Drafts, Notes, Typescript (copy), 1963 (Box 3)
  - A Piece of the Action--Notes and Reviews (copy), 1962 (Box 3)
  - Russian People by Constantine Simonov (acting version by Odets), 1942 (Box 3)
  - The Show Must Go On-- Radio Original (copy), 1939 (Box 3)
  - The Story on Page One (temporary title)
    - 1958 October 1, (10 folders) (Box 3)
    - 1958 April 27, (2 folders) (Box 3)
    - First Draft Revised, undated, (3 folders) (Box 4)
    - Final Draft, circa 1959, (2 folders) (Box 4)
  - Waiting for Lefty, 1938 (Box 4)
  - Walk on the Wild Side (from the novel by Nelson Algren)
    - Final Draft, 1961 March 14, (3 folders) (Box 4)
    - undated (Box 4)
  - The Way West
    - First Draft, 1956 April, undated, (3 folders) (Box 4)
    - Notes on Treatment by Walter Newman, 1955 November 9 (Box 4)
    - Research Notebook, 1956-1957, (2 folders) (Box 4)
    - Research Notebook (compiled by Lelia Alexander), undated, (2 folders) (Box 4)
    - Section I, undated, (2 folders) (Box 4)
    - Section II, undated, (2 folders) (Box 4)
    - Step Outline by Walter Newman, 1955 December 12 (Box 4)
    - Typescript, 1957 September-October (11 folders) (Box 5)
  - Welcome to the City!, 1944 September 6, (3 folders) (Box 5)
  - The Whispering Cup, 1947 January 10, (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - A Winter Journey
    - Early Draft (copy), 1948, (2 folders) (Box 5)
    - First Draft (copy), undated, (2 folders) (Box 5)
    - Third Draft (copy), 1948 (Box 5)
- Series II: Personal Papers, 1937-1964
  Series II contains a small section of Clifford Odets' personal papers. These materials are primarily from 1960-1963. Included here are an assortment of clippings, ephemera, playbills, programs, and serials. There are a few pieces of scattered correspondence, including an anniversary announcement from Lee and Paula Strasberg, as well as letters from Milton Lipper to the Strasberg's following Odets' death in 1963. A program for Golden Boy, signed by Sammy Davis is present is this series. Additionally there is a letter from Courtois-Doybel to Jean Renoir sent along with a program for the French production of Le Grande Couteau (The Big Knife) from 1961. There are appointment books from Virginia Rowe, Odets' secretary, from 1958 and 1962.
  - The Actor--Typescript and Notes (copy), 1961 (Box 5)
  - Adams, Sue--Poems and Correspondence, 1958-1959 (Box 5)
  - The Adventures of the Black Girl in Her Search for God Samuel A. Boyea's Adaptation of George Bernard Shaw, undated (Box 5)
  - The Big Knife--Playbill and Reviews (in German), 1960 (Box 5)
  - Camille/15 Doves in Flight--Typescript, Notes, Articles, 1961 (Box 5)
  - Clippings, 1958-1962, (4 folders) (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1957-1964 (Box 6)
  - Ephemera, 1958-1962, (3 folders) (Box 6)
  - Films in Review, 1955 (Box 6)
  - Golden Boy--Programs (inscribed by Sammy Davis), 1964 (Box 6)
  - Le Grand Couteau (The Big Knife )--Program for French Production, Correspondence from Courtois-Doybel to Jean Renoir, 1961 (Box 6)
  - Kopland, Kenny and Cliff--Photographs, undated (Box 6)
  - Lakes Region Playhouse--The Country Girl --Playbill, undated (Box 6)
  - Lerner, Max--Columns, 1962 (Box 6)
  - A Lie a Century Long by Samuel A. Boyea (annotated), undated (Box 6)
  - Modern Screen, 1937 1938 (Box 6)
  - Noah, His Wife, and the Devil by Francis Lee Utley (inscribed to Clifford Odets), circa 1962 (Box 6)
  - Notes, 1961 undated (Box 6)
  - Portrait of a Playwright--Booklet by NBC Television Network, 1963 March (Box 6)
  - Private Treaty--Typescript and Notes (copy), 1961 (Box 6)
  - Reminders, 1961 (Box 6)
  - The Richard Boone Show--Booklet, 1962 (Box 6)
  - Rowe, Virginia (Odets' secretary)--Appointment Book, 1958, 1962, (2 folders) (Box 6)
  - Serials and Journals (various), 1962 (Box 6)
  - Sister Carrie--Notes by Virginia Rowe, 1944 (Box 6)
  - Sum and Substance, 1963 (Box 6)
  - Theatre Arts, 1963 May (Box 6)
  - Waiting for Lefty-- Comparison Copy (copy), 1939 (Box 6)